Well, thank you all so much again for joining us. We just wrapped up a series on solitude, and next week we are launching a series on the Book of Ruth, which I am very, very excited about. But what I am probably as excited about, if not more excited about, is our guest speaker this morning. We are welcoming a friend that is connected to us through the denomination.
I'm calling her a new friend of mine. She came out to lead our women in their conference yesterday. We had seven churches with 65 women here yesterday, which is awesome. Sarah is a published author and mother and cool person, so please give her a warm canvas welcome.
Am I on? Am I on? Okay. Good morning, everybody. Cool person. I don't know if I can agree with that, but I'm going to go with it, so thank you. I am also, I work from home, and I don't normally wear dress shoes, so I'm going to say this is holy ground and take off my shoes because my toes are starting to go numb, and I just, I guess my feet don't fit in those shoes anymore.
So, I am really delighted to be here with you and worshiping with you this morning. It was just wonderful. I feel so blessed. I always weep during worship, so I was like, "Oh, gosh. This is going to be bad." But thank you.
I have the distinct honor of standing before you today in what I call prime real estate on the church calendar. Right between Ash Wednesday, when we're reminded that we are dust and
just shall return and the start of Lent, when many people in the family of God commemorate Christ's 40 days in the wilderness by making the ultimate sacrifice, giving up chocolate.
Here we are, caught between our own mortality and voluntary suffering. What a comforting place to be right now. There's nothing like a little existential dread and self-denial to really set the tone for the season.
In this perfect storm of dust and deprivation, I want to point out the face in the eye of this hurricane. Anxiety.
Maybe you recognize this character from Pixar's Inside Out 2. This is Anxiety. She is the queen of over-preparation and over-analysis. When she's allowed to reign over our fear and our suffering,
she can create quite the storm of self-doubt and panic attacks. But let's be honest, life gives us plenty to be anxious about.
We worry about our families, our jobs, our health, the state of the world. Some of us are even anxious about what we should give up for Lent.
While anxiety is a normal human emotion and something we all experience in different ways, sometimes she can turn into a beast.
God and His goodness has given us His Word, His Spirit, His community, and His creation as ways to help us fight against the spirit of fear and anxiety that threatens to take us down.
Today, as we stand in this tension between the reminder of our limits and the call to rely on God, I want to explore what it means to face our anxiety with faith.
To bring our fears into God's presence, and to trust that we are held, even when life feels uncertain.
When I feel anxious about practically anything, it helps me to remember this reality:
For I am convinced that neither death nor life, neither angels nor demons, neither the present nor the future, nor any powers, neither height nor depth,
anything else in all creation, will be able to separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
Romans 8:38-39. It's easy for us to plow through that set of verses and feel lightly inspired. I got a few amens, I heard.
So I'd like to read it again to you, slower and even more dramatically this time.
For I am convinced that neither death nor life, neither angels nor demons, neither the present nor the future, nor any powers,
neither height nor depth, nor anything else in all creation, will be able to separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
Nothing in creation can separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
I don't think that you're feeling the full weight of this passage yet, so we're just going to keep on saying it over and over for the next 30 minutes.
Let's start with neither death nor life. This little bit is especially pertinent on the heels of Ash Wednesday.
Nothing can separate us from God's love in Jesus Christ, not living and not dying. Saint Benedict and other monks of old incorporated the
phrase "memento mori" into their spiritual practice. Memento mori means remember that you must die.
I realize this might seem counterintuitive to the whole anxiety-reducing objective of this sermon, but stick with me.
When I remember that none of us gets out of here alive, it has a way of right-sizing my problems. Practically nothing I am worried about today has eternal consequences.
And nothing I am worried about can separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord, not even dying.
Okay, neither angels nor demons. As much as C.S. Lewis' demons in the screw-tape letters or the spiritual forces depicted in John Milton's Paradise Lost might try, even the supernatural world that we don't understand
but love to imagine, can't get between us and God's love. Neither good spirits nor evil spirits, they can't stand against the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
How about the present or the future? What present and future challenges feel like barriers to accessing God's love?
Perhaps you are afraid you're going to miss God's plan for you.
Perhaps you are afraid of losing your job. Perhaps you are afraid you'll be found out for who you really are.
Perhaps you are afraid your child will not choose to be the person you envision them becoming.
Perhaps you are afraid of where the world is headed. Perhaps you are afraid you aren't a good enough Christian.
Perhaps you are afraid you will never measure up to earn your place in God's kingdom.
Brothers and sisters in Christ, let me join my voice with Paul, who says, "The Spirit you received does not make you slaves, so that you live in fear again.
Rather, the Spirit you received brought about your adoption to sonship, and by him we cry, "Abba, Father."
Nothing in the present or the future is beyond the loving embrace of "Abba, Father."
Well, what about those powers? There are lots of powers and principalities in the world, both foreign and domestic, that are conjuring up all kinds of anxieties today.
Of all of the things to be worried about, it would seem that this is a concern we ought to be worried about.
After all, in Ephesians, Paul reminds us that our struggle isn't against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities, against the powers of this dark world, and against the spiritual forces of evil in the heavenly realms.
Interesting enough, Paul doesn't urge us to take up weapons of war to go to battle against the powers.
If that was what Jesus expected us to do, he might have set up a different example for us the night that he was betrayed.
He had every opportunity, and even a band of brothers, ready to pick up arms on his behalf.
Peter even made a go at it, but Jesus told him, "Put your sword back in its place, for all who draw the sword will die by the sword."
To help us understand how we ought to face the powers and principalities of this dark world,
Paul invites us to wear the belt of truth, don the breastplate of righteousness,
fit our feet with the gospel of peace, and hold in front of us the shield of faith.
And what is the shield of faith? Our belief that there is nothing that can separate us from the love of God
that is in Christ Jesus, our Lord. These words from Paul should empower us
to stand firm in our conviction to follow Christ, who is the way, the truth, and the life,
wielding the sword of truth, which is the word of God, as we face individual and systemic injustices,
defend the poor, feed the hungry, care for the widows and orphans, heal the sick, and shelter the outsider.
All right, let's scoot along into the final leg of this verse. Neither height nor depth,
nor anything else in all creation. In all of creation, Christ and the love of God that is in Christ Jesus, our Lord.
I got real good at memorizing this verse when I was working on this sermon, by the way.
In all of creation, Christ reigns supreme.
In Colossians 1, verses 15 through 20, Paul tells the church of Colossae,
"The sun is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn over all creation.
For in him all things were created, things in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible,
whether thrones or powers or rulers or authorities. All things have been created through him and for him.
He is before all things, and in him all things hold together.
And he is the head of the body, the church. He is the beginning and the firstborn from among the dead,
so that in everything he might have the supremacy. For God was pleased to have all his fullness dwell in him,
and through him to reconcile to himself all things, whether things on earth or things in heaven,
by making peace through his blood shed on the cross.
I love how many times Paul says all things in this passage of Scripture,
as if to really hit home how supreme Christ is. He's the firstborn over all creation.
In him all things were created. All things have been created through him and for him. He is before all things.
In him all things hold together. Is there anything outside of all things?
No, there's nothing outside of all things. Way back in the second century AD,
Irenaeus, who is one of the early church fathers, developed what we call today the two-books theology.
According to Irenaeus, God has written for us two books. I bet you didn't know that.
A big book of creation, and a little book, the Bible.
And that is through, that it is through both of these so-called books, that God has chosen to reveal his character.
I love this because I love being out in nature.
A little side note, we had a really lovely time hiking in Shenandoah before coming here this week.
It's just glorious. So your backyard is very beautiful.
We have the incredible privilege to live during a time of substantial scientific advancement.
We can see far greater heights than we've ever seen before.
Scientists now estimate that there are somewhere between 200 billion to 2 trillion galaxies in the known universe.
All creation is far higher and wider than we can even imagine.
At the same time, we can also zoom in to the greatest depths to examine the very framework of all of creation.
In my lifetime, we were once pretty sure that the atom was the building block, the smallest particle in creation.
Then we discovered that there were more bits and pieces to the atom,
and then we learned that there were even smaller bits and pieces inside those bits and pieces.
All creation is far deeper and complex than we can even imagine.
And yet, science is once again confirming what the wisdom teachers have been declaring for centuries.
All things are interconnected.
"We are stardust brought to life, then empowered by the universe to figure itself out," says agnostic scientist Neil deGrasse Tyson.
"But we know the one who empowers the universe. It is in Christ that all things hold together."
I said at the beginning that this is a sermon on anxiety, sandwiched between death and suffering.
We've peered into creation to see how high and wide and long and deep the love of God is that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
If God's love is that high and that wide and that long and that deep, and we can't be separated from it, that should give us so much confidence.
In the grand scheme of things, nothing can separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
But God is not just a God of the universal. God is also a God of the particular.
And we can't talk about anxiety without talking about the birds and the flowers.
As part of Jesus's most famous sermon, he told his followers,
"Therefore I tell you, do not worry about your life, what you will eat or drink, or about your body, what you will wear.
Is not life more than food, and the body more than clothes?
Look at the birds of the air. They do not sow or reap or store away in barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them.
Are you not much more valuable than they? Can any one of you be worrying by worrying at a single hour to your life?
And why do you worry about clothes? See how the flowers of the field grow? They do not labor or spin.
Yet I tell you that not even Solomon, in all his splendor, was dressed like one of these.
If that is how God clothes the grass of the field, which is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the fire, will he not much more clothe you, you of little faith?
So do not worry, saying, "What shall we eat?" or "What shall we drink?" or "What shall we wear?"
For the pagans run after all of these things, and your heavenly Father knows that you need them.
But seek first his kingdom and his righteousness, and all these things will be given to you as well.
Therefore, do not worry about tomorrow, for tomorrow will worry about itself.
Each day has enough trouble of its own. God does not only care about the grand plan of his coming kingdom.
God doesn't just hold all of eternity in the palms of his hands. God also sees you. He loves you. He cares for you.
Everything, even you, are held in the immensity of God's love.
The psalmist sings of this intimate reality, this way God knows you personally, in Psalm 139.
For you created my inmost being. You knit me together in my mother's womb.
I praise you because I am fearfully and wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful. I know that full well.
My frame was not hidden from you when I was made in the secret place, when I was woven together in the depths of the earth.
Your eyes saw my unformed body. All the days ordained for me were written in your book before one of them came to be.
All of this allows us to trust that God holds all things together, no matter what happens. No matter what.
We can spin out every kind of worst-case scenario and still land on this grand truth.
Nothing can separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
Our belief in the reality of God's love should revolutionize the way we live our lives.
We are set free by this great love. Through Christ's love, we no longer conform to the patterns of this world, but are transformed by the renewing of our minds.
Through Christ, we are given abundant life. We are empowered by the Holy Spirit
to love the unlovable, called to reflect the image of God that is in every single human being, so they can see and believe that they too are loved with an everlasting love.
So that they too can be set free of the shackles of sin and death, and truly live by the grace of God, with peace that passes all understanding and joy that overflows.
Empowered by the confidence of God's great love, every single person we meet, from the moment we wake up to the second we put our heads on our pillows, is a person we can extend God's love to.
Not looking past the unlovable, or the strange, or the outsider, but instead seeing the image of God in them. Treating them as children of God. Loving them as Christ loves us.
This kind of foundation reframes every interaction we have with other human beings, even our enemies.
God has already done the work. God has already said that we are redeemed, once and for all, through the work of Christ on the cross, so that nothing can separate us from the love of God.
But we just don't always believe it. I just don't always believe it. It is easy for me to forget that nothing can separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus, our Lord.
As I wait for blood work and test results, it is easy to forget that nothing can separate me from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus, my Lord.
As my children trip and stumble through their own sequence of existential questions, it is easy for me to forget that nothing can separate them from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus, our Lord.
As I scroll through social media and watch the unfolding apocalypse, it is easy to forget that nothing can separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus, our Lord.
So, I join my voice with the Father in Mark chapter 9, verse 24, who said to Jesus, "I do believe. Help me overcome my unbelief."
You see, in my head, I believe that Christ Jesus is Lord. I believe He's the way, the truth, and the life. But sometimes, in my heart, I'm not so sure.
My heart says, "That's nice, what you believe about God, brain. But are you sure He's got this? Even this? Are you sure?"
Because maybe I need to take matters into my own hands and worry about this thing that is completely beyond my control. That seems really productive.
The redemptive work of Christ is done, once and for all. But we still live in the reality of right now.
And there will always be this part of us on this side of the grave that just isn't so sure He is faithful.
His faithfulness never ceases. I believe it. So Lord, help me overcome my unbelief.
Help me open up the vice grip of control I have of my life in my fists and trust that you are really the way, the truth, and the life.
Help me walk in your ways so I can truly experience the indescribable, uncontainable love of the Father and peace Christ promised.
The world is full of trouble. Jesus did not promise to rescue us from this sandwich of suffering and death.
Instead, he said, "I have told you these things so that in me you may have peace. In this world you will have trouble, but take heart. I have overcome the world."
Take heart, heart. Jesus has overcome the world. I cling to these promises from Jesus, and when my anxiety rises over that which is out of my control,
I seek reminders in nature, in my community, in prayer, and in Scripture of the love that holds all things together.
I join my shaky, anxious voice with 14th century church mystic Julian of Norwich, who said, "All shall be well. All shall be well. All manner of things shall be well."
When anxiety rises up in your life, I pray that you, being rooted and established in that great love, may have power, together with all the Lord's holy people,
to grasp how wide and long and high and deep is the love of Christ, and to know this love that passes under our knowledge, that you may be filled to the measure of all the fullness of God.
May the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord be the foundation that gives us the ability to stand firm in times of fear and uncertainty,
and continue to do the good work the Lord has called us to do. Amen. Will you join me in prayer?
Oh, Father, thank you so much for being with us this morning. Thank you for your amazing presence that holds all things together,
that holds me together, and catches all of my nerves into a little container and says, "Be confident."
Lord, thank you that you hold our world together, that no matter what is happening,
the powers and the principalities in our families and in our friend groups, in our church and in our communities,
you hold all things together. Your love conquers all. I thank you so much for these people.
I thank you for the opportunity to gather here this morning for your amazing word that reassures us that you have a love
for us that is everlasting. I pray that you would be with us here today as we continue to lift our eyes and our hearts
and our minds to you and be with us as we leave this precious day.
Take my shoes and my water that I didn't drink and my paperclip.
We're going to conclude our service by taking the bread and the cup of communion.
I wanted to read a verse before we did so as we contemplate what we're doing when we come up and get this little cube of bread and this small cup of juice.
It's so much more than what we often think about when we approach the table.
We talked about at our Ash Wednesday service that I think that there's a way in which we can preach the gospel in the church in America that so emphasizes what God did on the cross, that it totally ignores any invitation for us to follow him to that same cross.
And we even do that in communion. Oftentimes, I do that, and I think it's good to remember in communion that the body broken for us, the blood shed for us, is the finished work on the cross, that there is nothing that we can do to inherit our salvation.
There is nothing we can do to earn our salvation. It is a free gift from God and from God alone. And yet, we read words from Jesus like this in Matthew chapter 16.
Then Jesus said to his disciples, "Whoever wants to be my disciple must deny themselves, take up their cross, and follow me.
For whoever wants to save their life will lose it, but whoever loses their life for me will find it.
What good will it be for someone to gain the whole world and yet forfeit their soul?
Or what can anyone give in exchange for their soul? For the Son of Man is going to come in the Father's glory with his angels,
and then he will reward each person according to what they have done."
And so at Canvas, we practice an open communion. That means you don't have to be a member of our church to take this.
It's between you and the Lord, but communion is a thing that is set up by Jesus for his followers.
And so this morning as we come to the table to partake in communion, I was thinking about the song we sang,
at first, lead me to the cross. And that's often a song that when I sing it, I think about Jesus leading me to the cross to receive his forgiveness and his grace, his mercy and his love.
But I think just like communion is a reminder for us to experience his grace, his mercy, his forgiveness, his love.
It's also an invitation for us to follow Jesus's example, to lay down our life for those around us, to pick up our cross and to follow after him.
And so this morning, as we take communion, I'd love for you to think about not only what God has done for you by going to the cross, but what he's invited you to follow him into.
To follow his example of laying down our life, serving and loving others wholly imperfectly, which is again, the beauty of the reminder of God's forgiveness and grace at the table is you and I are going to fail 10 minutes after
we leave this door. Some of us five minutes after we leave this door. Some of us before we get out of the room. But that does not negate the invitation that Jesus' mercies are new every morning.
Every moment of every day, we have the opportunity to repent and to move forward in obedience to Jesus. And so I think we have a map on the screen. We do.
I'm going to dismiss you for those of you who want to say, "I want to remind myself of God's grace and forgiveness through His broken body and shed blood."
But not only that, I want to take seriously His invitation to follow His example. I'd invite you to come and grab the elements.
And once you get them and get seated, we will take them together. So, go ahead.